Your Majesty
폐하
Why have you come here?
여긴 어찌 오셨습니까
Rise
일어나거라
Your Majesty
폐하
You shouldn't move around
움직이지 마십시오
It's cold now
지금은 날씨가 추우니
When the weather warms up later
이따 따뜻해지면
I'll take you for a good walk
그때 산책하시지요
What
왜
Is there something wrong with my body?
짐의 몸에 무슨 문제가 있느냐
Your Majesty
폐하
Of course there's nothing wrong with Your Majesty's body
폐하의 건강에는 당연히 문제가 없습니다
You then
너도 가자꾸나
Take a team
사람을 끌고
With me
나와 함께
Following behind Your Majesty
폐하의 뒤를 따르라
I promise you all
내가 약속하겠네
Great Xuan has never forgotten the people of the north
선나라는 단 하루도 북방 백성들을 잊은 적이 없으니
The royal army will recover the lost territories
아군은 반드시 고향을 수복하여
And restore peace to all
모두에게 평화로운 세상을 돌려주겠네
This northern expedition
그놈의 북벌
You're risking your life for it
왕야만 목숨 걸고 하네요
Xuan Kingdom's greatest enemy
선나라의 가장 큰 적은
Has never been in the north
종래로 북방에 있지 않았어
Minister Chen means
진 승상의 생각은 어떤가
What else does Your Highness want?
뭘 원하시는지 말씀하세요
My friendship
저의 우정을
Does Your Highness dare to want it?
감히 받을 수 있겠어요
We're not yet established
우리 아직은 완전히 발붙이지 못했으니
It's not yet time to move against them
그들을 건드릴 때가 아니야
Today the Ministry of Revenue calculated tax revenue
올해 호부의 총 세수는
Totaling over 18 million taels
1,800여만 냥입니다
Can shield Your Highness from wind and rain, block swords and spears
전하를 위해 비바람을 막고 창칼을 물리칠 수 있어서
It is Huan's fortune
영광입니다
Your Highness, this old minister finally sees you
전하 드디어 뵙네요
If you stay away too long
밖에서 너무 오래 계시면
I'll name the child myself
제가 아이 이름을 짓겠습니다
Speaking of defeat before the battle
싸우기도 전에 패배를 말하다니요
Since it's a fight to the death, I won't be a coward
싸우다 죽을지언정 겁쟁이 안 해
Your Majesty, what do you need?
폐하 무슨 일 있으시면
Just order your servant to do it
바로 분부하십시오
Five hundred it is
5백이면 뭐 어때요
Five hundred men strike first
5백이서 선수 치면 되죠
No more talk, come
쓸데없이 상대하지 말고 자
Prince of Jin is rebelling
진왕이 역모를 꾀했다
I am ordered to capture him
난 명을 받고 잡으러 왔다
Surrender
순순히 오라를 받으면
And your lives will be spared
목숨은 살려주마
This northern expedition
이번 북벌의
Our goal is to recapture Beiyu Pass
목표는 북역관을 되찾는 것이다
Your Highness, Prince of Jin
진왕 전하
I'm Liu Dadao
유대도라 하오
Commander of the Yong'an Garrison Left Army
영안 수위 좌군 통령이오
Old brother, beat the drums for me
구 형 북을 울리게
Liu, Liu Nian
유 유념
Your Majesty
폐하
When you were in Yiyang, you promised Grandfather
익양에서 신첩 할아버지께 약속했잖아요
To protect your servant for a lifetime of peace and joy
신첩을 평생 무사하게 기쁘게 해주겠다고요
Your daughter bids farewell
소녀 작별 인사 올립니다
May Father Emperor take care of his sacred body
강녕하십시오 부황
Do you think the people kneel to you for nothing?
백성이 왜 너한테 나한테
They kneel to me, to Princess Xunyang
심양공주한테 무릎 꿇는데
Can't catch a wolf without sacrificing the child
호랑이 굴에 들어가야 호랑이 새끼를 잡는다고
Your son is willing to be the vanguard
소자가 선봉을 맡겠습니다
Murong Cui of Yan Dong
연동 모용최가
By order of Princess Xunyang
심양 공주의 명을 받들고
Come to reinforce
지원하러 왔습니다
It's all because of that Xuan Kingdom emperor
선나라 황제가 우릴
That got us into this situation
이 지경에 몰아넣었어
At this point, only this last plan remains
이렇게 된 이상 계책은 이제 하나뿐이다
This plan, he taught it to me
그자에게서 배운 것이지
Chu Meng
초몽
Do you know why I must go on the northern expedition?
짐이 왜 북벌을 고집하는지 아느냐
Your Majesty's achievements now surpass all past and present
폐하는 이미 전례 없는 공을 세웠습니다
The northern expedition requires money
북벌은 돈이 필요하고
Requires bloodshed
피를 흘려야 하며
Requires the sacrifice of several generations to complete
몇 세대에 걸친 희생이 있어야 성공할 수 있다
But I still must fight
짐은 그래도 싸울 것이야
Because this cannot be measured by profit
이 일은 이익으로 계산할 수 없어
Because Xuan Kingdom's people
왜냐하면 선나라 백성들이 집으로
They want to go home
돌아가고 싶어 하니까
They only recognize Xuan Kingdom as home
그들에게 집은 선나라뿐이니까
Look, look outside
봐봐 저 바깥쪽
Great victory, great victory
대승이다 대승이야
The royal army returns victorious
아군이 개선했다
Long live the Emperor
폐하 만세
In your lifetime
당신은 살면서
You achieved great merits
큰 공을 세웠고
And committed great mistakes
큰 잘못도 저질렀습니다
Some call you a ruthless tyrant
수단 방법을 안 가리는 폭군이라고 욕도 먹지만
But recovering the divine land
잃었던 땅을 수복한 것은
Is also an unparalleled achievement you created
당신이 세운 불세출의 업적입니다
Standing on this mountaintop
이 산꼭대기에 서서
You bear tens of thousands of people on your shoulders
당신은 수많은 백성의 삶을 짊어졌습니다
Subject to the judgment of later generations, history's pen is iron
후세에 어떤 평판과 기록으로 남을지 아랑곳하지 않고요
Along the way
그동안 당신이 겪었던
Love, hate, success, failure
사랑 미움 성공 실패
All rest on your single thought
모두 당신의 생각에 달린 것이었지요
The consequences of every choice
모든 선택의 결과는
You can only bear alone
스스로 감당할 수밖에 없습니다
Some heroes are made by history
어떤 영웅은 역사가 만들어낸 것이고
Make history
역사를 만듭니다
The ambition to look north at the realm
북방을 멀리 내다보며 했던 다짐들은
Will forever exist because of you
당신 때문에 영원히 존재합니다